in our Russia there are 5 million Ukrainians, 2
в нашей России живёт 5 млн украинцев 2
million or 3 million Kazakhs, 3 million Tatars and so
млн или 3 млн казахов 3 млн татар и так
on Yes How many schools in the Ukrainian
дальше Да Сколько школ на украинском
language are there in
языке есть в
Russia in Crimea How many schools are there in the
России в Крыму Сколько школ есть на
Ukrainian language in Russia look in
украинском языке в России смотри в
Tyumen in Moscow
Тюмене в Москве
where Crimea is
где Крым - это
Ukraine Hello you  where did I
Украина Здравствуйте Вы откуда из
understand from the Moscow region? I’m from Latvia, rub the city of Riga.
Подмосковья понял Я из Латвии город Рига
I ask people from Russia
потрите Я у людей из России спрашиваю
what about  Latvia, you know, you can
что вообще о Латвии знаете можете что-то
name something, you know, not so much, I probably
назвать знаете не так много наверное не
won’t come up with something right now, but it’s
буду сейчас что-то придумывать на при
interesting
вот интересно
that Yes, nothing special, an ordinary country, a
что Да ничего особенного обычная страна
small
небольшая
European Well, what can you find out,
европейская Ну а что можно узнать
some kind of rich history, I don’t remember
какая-то богатая история я не припоминаю
that
что Бога
you will defeat God with the Right A  tell me Why Do you think
победите А скажите Почему Как вы думаете
why when the Soviet Union collapsed,
почему когда Советский Союз распадался
Latvia wanted to be independent and did not
Латвия захотела быть независимой а не
want to live with
хотела жить с
Russia, you know then at one time
Россией вы знаете тогда в своё время
the Bolsheviks gave a lot of rights to all sorts of
большевики очень много наделили всяких
republics and the like  because of
республик правами и тому подобное из-за
this, they wanted purely only because of this,
этого и захотели чисто только изза этого
but if you read this, this is Marx as
но это если почитать Вот это Маркса как
communists, like I think that it was a little
коммунистов подобно Я считаю что немного
bit wrong to give many
чуть неправильно было наделять много
republics autonomy, that is, there are some
республик автономии то есть там каким-то
say very large rights Well, that is,
сказать очень большими пра Ну то есть
purely purely Well,
именно чисто Ну
maybe you wanted  you know In what year and
захотели Может вы знаете В каком году и
how Latvia became part of the Soviet
как Латвия вошла в состав Советского
Union you know Probably I think that how
Союза вы знаете Наверно я думаю что как
many territories
многие территории
were due to the war Probably something like this And
было из-за войны Наверно как-то так А
what war and in what years approximately well,
какой войны и в каких годах примерно ну
I’m not I’m not a historian  you see, I can
вот я не я не историк понимаете Я могу
guess, but I’m not a historian. Just guess,
предположить но я не историк
I’m just a historian, I’m a
Предположите Да просто я историк я
historian, I’m a historian at the University of Riga,
историк я историк Рижского университета
I’m interested in how much people from
мне интересно да насколько люди из
Russia know our history, in what
России знают нашу историю вот в каком
year or so. Well, I don’t know,
приблизительно году Ну не знаю
probably not. Latvia, you know, I won’t lie
наверное нет Латвия знаете не буду врать
because I’m now something-  I’ll say
потому что я сечас что-нибудь скажу
some years, then they’ll put it on the
какие-нибудь года потом нибудь в
Internet and they’ll look completely stupid
интернет выложат и будут совсем глупо
no No, look here I’m
выглядеть не Нет вотт смотрите Тут мне
just wondering how people are at least
просто интересно насколько люди хотя бы
approximately Titus, you’re not in an
приблизительно Тит это ж вы же не на
exam, just at least according to
экзамене просто вот хотя бы по ощущениям
your feelings in what years it was  was
вашим в каких это годах было в Советский
Latvia got into the Soviet Union Well, probably in
Союз попала Латвия Ну наверное в
the forties there before with right Yes 1939
сороковых там до со правильно Да 1939
yes yes in 1939 uh Soviet Union
год да да в 1939 году э Советский Союз
Hitler's Germany signed a pact of
гитлеровский Германия подписал пакт
ground children on the division of uh Europe
молотого ребен ропа о разделе ээ Европы
attacked
напали на
Poland USSR attacked Latvia Lithuania
Польшу СССР напал на Латвию Литву
Estonia well, you probably know that
Эстонию ну вы знаете наверное вот
interpreting
трактовать
Pak as what you just said about
Пак как то что вы сейчас сказали и о том
dividing Europe is probably
чтобы разделить Европу это наверное
a little
чуть-чуть
wrong. That’s why you have a historian
неправильно Потому у вас историк
involved. No, not a historian, but me too  as
включился Нет не историк но я тоже как
if, well, he was looking at something, reading something,
бы ну что-то смотрел что-то читал
firstly, whenever there was an attack on Paul,
во-первых при когда бы нападение на Поль
he forgot his memory does not change those territories
он заб память не изменяет те территории
that were originally, respectively, in the
которые изначально были соответственно в
Russian Empire when no no
Российской империи когда нет нет
for example, look at the city of Lvov, look at the
например смотрите город Львов смотрите
city of Lvov, was not in the Russian Empire
город Львов не был в Российской империи
city  Lvov was in the Austro-Hungarian
город Львов был в австро-венгерской
Empire. Well, I mean that when
Империи Ну я имею в виду то что когда
we had a civil war, Poland
был у нас гражданская война Польша этим
took advantage of this and took
воспользовался И забрала себе там
some two territories there for itself. Stalin simply
какие-то две территории Сталин просто их
returned them to himself, which territories he did not take.
вернул себе какие территории забрала не
See the section again.  When you had a civil
смотрите Когда у вас была гражданская
war, there was an independent here, that's where it is
война тут было независимое вот где это
Poland, here there were independent these UPR Zurr
Польша тут были независимые эти УНР зунр
Poland And so on,
Польша И так дальше гражданская война у
you had a civil war in Russia, and no one took anything from you there, are
вас была в России да у вас ничего там
you all there,
никто не забирал вы все там ли друг
red white, as usual, yes yes  but
друга красные белые как обычно да да но
Poland then took the territory, what
Польша то забрала территорию какую какую
territory did Poland take for itself, well,
территорию забрала себе Польша ну
type it in on the Internet, so you tell me
забейте в Интернете у так вот вы скажите
which region Well, it
какой какую область Ну это мне сейчас
just works out for me now, I need to
просто получается на надо сейчас
fill it in now,
забивать
m Trans-Baikal Territory zab Poland what
м Забайкальский край заб Польша что
Kalmykia I now I need to look for it
калмыкию я сейчас мне нужно искать это
was it was a fact Poland took it Stalin
было это факт Польша забрала Сталин себе
returned it further to Poland Without dividing well, is
вернул он дальше польш Не разделя ну
there a Fact is there a fact is it good and for and
есть ли Факт есть ли факт хорош а по а
for Finland Why Finland was attacked by Finland
по Финляндии Почему на Финляндию
in my opinion there are no names
напала Финляндию на помоему мнем уб имен
in this
в это
conli
конли
nor
ни
finland you know  Well, then the situation
финлянди вы знаете Ну тогда ситуация
was the same. But how is it possible? I didn’t quite understand
тоже была А как можно Я не совсем понял
how to move the border, if you move the
как отодвинуть границу если отодвинуть
border away from the USSR, you
границу от СССР вы
move away and
отодвигается и
the border, I answer you, Stalin asked  at
грани я вам отвечаю Сталин попросил на
that moment because the borders were very
тот момент потому что границы очень были
close to us And he asked them to move
близко к нам И он попросил их отодвинуть
there, in principle, he
там в принципе он
understands that, uh, the border was close to you
этож понимаю э граница была близко к вам
if the border the border is always close to you
если граница граница всегда близка к вам
Russian Finnish war again, see
российско финская война ещё раз смотрите
What is the border between two
Что такое граница между двумя
states This is where one  the state
государствами Это где одно государство
is in contact with another the border is always
соприкасается с другим граница всегда
close to the state, there is no closer anymore
близко к госуда ближе уже не
there were very close borders if
бывает очень тесные были границы если
my memory serves me right I just you
мне память не изменяет Я просто вы меня
asked me I answer you I’m not saying that
спросили я вам отвечаю Я не говорю что
this is exactly the case I’m saying in my opinion yes
это именно так я говорю по-моему да
Stalin asked  to push back the border, he
Сталин попросил отодвинуть границу он
was ready to compensate because their
готов был компенсировать мто там ихние
affairs were there at that time, but the Finns did not
дела были да в то время но фины не
want to do it and they had to,
захотели это сделать и пришлось как бы
well, as usual in the whole world, a
ну как обычно во всм мире начинается
war begins to be decided, wait, I understood correctly
решаться вое подожди я правильно понял
that the Soviet Union attacked Finland
что Советский Союз напал на Финляндию
to push back the
чтобы отодвинуть
border
границу
Well, partly Yes  probably that is, so that
Ну отчасти Да наверно то есть чтоб
Finland would be further away from the Soviet
Финляндия была дальше от Советского
Union Yes, if they
Союза подальше Да так
were allies, this probably wouldn’t
были бы союзниками наверное такого бы не
happen, look at the task Let’s have a task for the
было смотри задача Давай задача для
first class Look, here’s the USSR, here’s
первого класса Смотри вот СССР вот
Finland, yes  The USSR does not understand that
Финляндия да СССР не понимает что
Finland is very close and the USSR pushed back the
Финляндия очень близко и СССР отодвинула
border with Finland, but Finland is
границу с Финляндией но Финляндия жето
still close to the USSR, it
всё равно близко к СССР
turns out no. If Finland had to have
получается нет Если Финляндия должна
its own
была своий
borders, look again, the Soviet Union
границ ещё раз смотри Советский Союз
attacked Finland and pushed back, took a
напал на Финляндию и отодвинул забрал
piece of territory. Yes, with cities, for example, the city of
кусок территории Да с городами вот город
Vyborg Yes  and others don’t look,
Выборг например Да и другие не смотрите
I told you my reason, you can
я вам сказал свою причину вы мне можете
explain yours to me Why the USSR attacked
объяснить свою Почему ССР напал на
Finland Why Okay, let’s
Финляндию Почему Хорошо давай давайте
look at it this way, you tell me your opinion I’m
смотрите вы мне скажите своё мнение Я
here  so my opinion I can’t understand at all
вот так моё моё мнение Я не могу Совсем
look the distance from the USSR to
понять смотрите расстояние от СССР до
Finland was 0 cm after that yes Stalin
Финляндии был 0 сме после это да Сталин
decided that it was very close and moved the
решил что это сильно близко и отодвинул
border and the distance between the USSR and
границу и и расстояние между ССР и
Finland still remained 0 cm
Финляндией всё равно осталось 0 см
tried to move the borders so he
пытался отодвинуть границ так он
moved it tried so  he pushed back the
отодвинул пытался так он отодвинул зах
city of Vyborg, captured by
как вот город Выборг захваченный
Finland,
Финляндией
friends Well, how can I tell you this is a
други Ну это уже как вам сказать
consequence of the war Well, he pushed back the borders
следствие войны Ну вот отодвинул границы
and again stood near
и снова стал возле
Finland Well, that means
Финляндии Ну значит нужно было бы нужно
he should have needed this part of the territory  borrow
было эту часть территории ему занять для
why is this a strategic question I do
чего это стратегический вопрос я негу
n’t like that Finland is near the borders of the USSR
не нрави что Финляндия возле границ ССР
why Stalin didn’t want to push back the
почему Сталин не захотел отодвинуть
border of the USSR so that there would be no Finland Well,
границу СССР чтобы Финляндии не было Ну
would you want to no, well, Stalin is Stalin
вы бы захотели бы нет ну Сталин есть
That is, as if such a person is
Сталин То есть как бы личность такая
quite serious in world history
достаточно серьёзная в мировой истории
Don’t laugh  after all, this is a man
Не надо смеяться всё-таки это человек
who was very much respected and who respected
кото очень сильно уважали и кто уважал
him everyone And who didn’t respect him everyone
его все А кто его не его уважали все его
respected him he was respected all over the
уважали его уважали во всём
world everything absolutely specific navite who
мире все абсолютно конкретно навите кто
respected
уважал
everyone  world leaders respect him,
Все мировые лидеры его уважают это вы
where did you get this from? And what didn’t happen?
откуда взяли такое А что такого не было
Well, Churchill wrote that Stalin was
Ну вон Черчиль писал что Сталин был
Paranoid, like he didn’t respect him at all.
Параноик типа вообще его не уважал
Churchill Yes, Roosevelt didn’t respect him either, like
Черчиль Да Рузвельт не уважал тоже типа
Stalin, who respected Stalin? Well, but when
Сталина кто уважал Сталина Ну зато когда
they met after the Second World War, when
они после Второй Мировой Войны когда
this  the whole coalition and when
собралась вот эта вся коалиция и ког
Where did you run away
Куда ты убежал
and
а
Kolya Light sand comment
Коли Лайт песочка комент
wonder what you are
интересно что это вы
doing Well in general in general  crane on the
делаете Ну вообще вообще на кране на
crane Pony Can you show the view from the
кране Поня А можете показать вид из
cabin crane Well, you see where the phone is, where am I
кабины Ну вы видите где телефон где я
damn it, it’s interesting those pony
блин это интересно те пони
crane in the port and the height is nothing
кран в порту а высота какая ничего
interesting 14 M
интересно 14 М
cool I now understand how short
прикольно Я теперь понимаю как короче
these videos are when something is from a crane crane
вот эти видео когда что-то с крана кран
what  - something will blow away or something will fall Yes,
что-то снесёт или что-то упадёт Да
the crane operators are just sitting on roulette, not really, now it’s
крановщики не на самом деле сейчас
just work such that there are no people below
просто работа такая что людей внизу нет
and work in the warehouse, so you can play around
и работа по складу так можно баловаться
eating  options
есть варианты
Yes, you can pamper It’s just so interesting It
Да можно баловать Просто так интересно
looks like you’re sitting on the toilet, you know, it looks like this, they’re
знаете выглядит такая вот так вот они
all the same taps, you can climb on any and
все одинаковые краны на любой залазишь и
sit like on a potty, there’s heating on the
сидишь как на горшке обогрев есть на
taps, it turns out that there’s heating
кранах получается что обогрев
Well, here’s the cabin with an air conditioner and
есть Ну вот здесь кабини кондиционер и
two stoves Yeah, so that it’s winter  not
две печки Ага чтобы зима не
to freeze Well, I’m
замерзнуть Ну вот я сижу мне сейчас вот
sitting here now in a thin sweater, and I’m wildly hot right now, I
в тонком свитере сижу и мне сейчас дико
realized, well, the cabin, the cabin was still
жарко понял ну кабина кабина ещё была
cold  I’m still going to shoot everything right now
остывшая я всё повча вот сейчас
through the letter you yourself
уже через литер буду снимать вы сами
where is the city of Tuapse about Tuapse I know this is the
откуда город туапс о Туапсе знаю это
port where the oil
порт где нефтяной
terminal is not where
терминал нет где
Suko is heavy in short the terminal I understood that
Суко грузный короче терминал понял вот
there drones flew into this oil terminal
там в терминал этот нефтяной прилетали
I know in that option not to the
беспилотники знаю в той опции не в
terminal not to the terminal And
терминал не в терминал А
where  they flew into the installation of the
куда они прилетали в установка
primary Ashka Yes,
первичной Ашка Да
Ashka
Ашка
understood it was interesting that they
понял интересно
flew into it
в неё в неё прилетала
and Well, once they successfully
и Ну один раз прямо успешно
repaired it for 3 weeks. Well, the second time it was already
ремонтировали Ну а второй раз уже
so meager, in short, I understood, well, the Germans
так на мизера короче понял ну немцы
will give  these Tarus missiles will no longer be on the
дадут эти ракеты Тарус будет уже не на
Mizra. Well, let’s just say they’re already
мизрах Ну скажем так тут жеже
prepared for something. Well, it’s logical. Well, I think
подготовились Ну логично же Ну я думаю
from what I see, they’re sitting there in Russia.
из того что я вижу да то в России там
And that a lot of them are clearly visible. Where
сидят А что много туда хорошо видно Где
Where are you sitting?
Где сидите Вы
Yes Well, okay And where  you are sitting in
да Ну хорошо А где вы сидите
Dresden Well, in Germany Yes, it’s clear
Дрезден А ну в Германии Да хорошо видно
what’s happening in Russia for sure
что в России делается наверняка
[music]
[музыка]
I don’t know I’m not from Ukraine I’m originally
Я не знаю я Я не из Украины Я сам родом
from Rostov, I just live in Germany But I
из Ростова просто в Германии живу Но я
support
поддерживаю
Ukraine Why Well, because Russia is
Украину А почему Ну потому что Россия
a state  attacked a neighboring country,
государство напало на соседнюю страну на
Ukraine Have you ever been to
Украину А вы когда-нибудь бывали на
Ukraine?
Украине
Never lived
никогда пожи
Yes, when it was a republic of the USSR,
Да когда она была республикой СССР
never lived there with anyone, did not communicate, did
никогда ни с кем там не жили не общались
not travel through it; you don’t understand what we’re
не ездили по ней не понимаете о чём
talking about there. What does this country consist of?
вообще там идёт речь Из чего состоит эта
people, how they were raised, how they
людей как они были воспитаны как они
were brought up in the Soviet Union, how they were
воспитывались в Советском Союзе как они
raised
воспитаны
now, you don’t know the language,
сейчас не знаете языка
they have the right to live the way they want,
они имеют право жить так как они хотят
we, Russia, have no right to attack them,
мы Россия не имеем права на них нападать
if we
если мы на них
attacked them, what difference does it make how they
напали какая разница как они там
live well there? Well  first of all, let's
живут хорошо Ну во-первых я начнём
start with the
начнём со
word
слова
Here's how it can be
Вот как может быть
applied, applicable nmda
примени применим нмда
lives 140-something damn nations and
живёт 140 с чем-то блин народов и
nationalities Just a second, I didn't
национально Секундочку секундочку я не
finish that, that is, more than 140
договорил то есть больше 140
nationalities and nationalities live in
национальностей и народностей живёт в
the country and you
стране и вы её
call it Yes, why I'm explaining, I'm
называете Да почему объясняю
explaining I didn't finish  I didn’t finish speaking,
объясняю не договорил я не договорил
plus on top of everything, there are more than 140
плюс ко всему вй кото живёт больше 140
nationalities and
национальностей народностей
nationalities with huge benefits
есть народности со льготами с огромными
Yes, small nations, so-
Да малые народы так
called,
называемые
who live on the territory of Ukraine for
вот на территории Украины кто проживает
how long? Let's now let me
сколько Дава давайте тепер давайте я вам
answer you, it means Look, I'm
теперь отвечу значит Смотри я вам
turning off the sound for you and listen to my answer, it
отключаю звук а послушайте мой ответ
means Russia is a state I lived in NM
значит Россия это государство я жил в НМ
Yes, I lived in Rostov Why You said it very
Да я жил в Ростове Почему Вот вы очень
correctly  There
правильно сказали у нас
are six of us nationalities there, yes, but for
там шесть народностей да живёт Да но
some reason
почему-то
Russian prohibits the development of the languages ​​of
российский запрещает развитие языков
these nationalities, the cultures of nationalities,
этих народностей культуры народности вот
look, uh, how much we have, look in in
смотрите ээ сколько у нас смотрите в в
ours, in our Russia, there are 5 million
нашей в нашей России живёт 5 млн
Ukrainians living 2 ml  or 3 million Kazakhs 3 million
украинцев 2 мл или 3 млн казахов 3 млн
Tatars and so on Yes How many schools in
татар и так дальше Да Сколько школ на
Ukrainian are there in
украинском языке есть в
Russia in Crimea How many schools are there in
России в Крыму Сколько школ есть на
Ukrainian in Russia look in
украинском языке в России смотрите в
Tyumen in Moscow where
Тюмени в Москве где
Crimea is
Крым - это
Ukraine you still have problems you look
Украина у тебя ещ проблемы вы смотрите в
5 million live in Russia  Ukrainians since the
России живёт 5 млн украинцев со врем
Soviet Union even and even before. Yes,
Советского Союза ещ да и раньше Да
name me at least one school there in the
назовите мне хоть одну школу там на
Ukrainian language,
украинском языке
teaching, Lord, teaching the Ukrainian
обучение Господи обучение украинскому
language is bad  riy
языку поно рии
ukra 666 different nationalities super And
укра 666 разных национальностей супер А
where are the schools that teach in the national
где школы на обучени на национальных
languages ​​of these and because the
языках этих а потому что
Russian says that there should
российский говорит что должен быть
only be a Russian language there should be only
только русский язык должна быть только
Russian culture they should
русская культура они должны читать
only read Pushkin Yes Lermontov and so
Пушкина только Да Лермонтова и так
on Yes, the
дальше Да вот
Russian nation is now oppressing a
э Российская нация сейчас угнетает
huge number  of this people, there is not a
огромное количество народа это и есть ни
single school, look, there is no
одной смотри ни одной школы Да нет на
education in the Jewish language, neither in German
еврейском языке обучения ни на немецком
nor in Ukrainian nor in Kazakh. I’m
ни на украинском ни на казахском Я же
talking about Millions of people and in  Germany
говорю Миллионы людей а в Германии ещё
again you said You said in Germany
раз вы сказали Вы сказали в Германии
Yes in Germany there is I I go to this
есть Да в Германии есть я я хожу в этот
my child goes to yes To a Russian-language
у меня ребёнок ходит да В русскоязычную
school and a friend has a Ukrainian-language school in
школу а у знакомого в украиноязычный в
Germany Yes there is a school with Ukrainian as the language of
Германии Да есть школа с украинским
instruction and with Russian as the language of
языком обучения и с русским языком
instruction in your Russia  there is with German
обучения у вас в России есть с немецким
or with
или с
Ukrainian that they teach in the Ukrainian
украинским что они учат на украинском
language Everything They teach the full course of study
языке Всё Они учат полный курс обучения
in the Ukrainian language But that is,
на украинском языке А вот то есть ты
look, you said I know, yes I know
смотри ты сказал Я же знаю да я же знаю
then, for example, our Russians say
дальше как например наши русские говорят
that Ukrainians do not exist, the Ukrainian
что украинцев не существует украинской
nation does not exist, this is the same thing
нации не существует это и есть Тоже
Hitler said, everything ruined my grandfather, my
Гитлер всё деда развалил
grandfather himself gave an example in which we
дед сам дал пример в котором мы его
destroyed him. But what if we have
уничтожили Да какой же если у нас там
600 66 nationalities there? Well, that’s the point
600 66 национальности Да вот в том-то и
case 666 and not a single school for 5
дело 666 и ни одного этого школы на 5
million Ukrainians, not a single Ukrainian
млн украинцев живёт ни одной украинской
school Why do they ban songs in
школы Почему Запрещают песни на
Ukrainian And so on Like this
украинском И так дальше Вот так лайк
squeak
писка комент Здравствуйте
comment Hello Hello Where are you from? We are from Rus' And where are you from? You come from Rostov but now I live in California 18 years later in 2 years it will be the twentieth Chernigov before it was now now now this is the Tmutarakan principality Krasnodar region Danya that would be well controlled not controlled there or so or otherwise the Russian prince, let’s say, reigned on these lands And there, just like for example, the Russian governor now has a province there  in Buryatia, for example, it doesn’t say anything, it’s the governor who collected the Tribute and you are a cockroach or who is your nationality. The thing is that there is, as it were, there is a concept you know metaphysics or Meta Meta terms Yes Rus' is already a term of such Meta quality and there is a sense of language You In general, you speak Russian well. Well, I’ve been speaking English for 18 years now, so I’ve forgotten Russian a little bit. I already speak metaphysics in English. It’s clear, and what’s your nationality? What’s my nationality?
там в Бурятии например это ничего не
Shapsug and even
шапсуг а даже
Shapsug, you know who the Shapsugs are,
шапсуг знаете кто такие шапсуги это у
yes, yes Shapsugs, there is even such a river as
вас да да шапсуги есть даже такая речка
Shapsug and there is even a Shapsugskaya
шапсуга и даже есть шапсугская
Wait for Shapsug, even in my opinion there
Подождите шапсуга даже по-моему село
is a village like that I don’t know Shapsugs - this is one of the
есть такое не знаю шапсуги - это одно из
Circassian tribes, we just inhabited
черкесских племён как раз мы населяли
this territory that is dark  cockroach the
вот это территорию которая тьмы таракан
principality then there was Well, yes, and Adyghe
княжество потом было Ну да да и Адыги
Ubykh Shapsugs this is yes this is
убыхи шапсуги это и есть да это есть
Circassians we are Circassians
черкес мы черкесы
Yes, well, they are called Circassian tribes,
Да ну черкесские их племена как бы
they just went there to Turkey
называют просто они ушли туда в Турцию
Yes, as it
Да как бы
turns out, the Russian Empire committed
получается Российская империя у сделала
genocide of the Circassians and the
геноцид черкесов и
exile of the Muhajir was there Not there precisely of their own free will. By their own
изг мухаджир было там Не там именно по
free will, most likely
доброй воле По доброй воле скорее всего
the Shapsugs went to the territory of Turkey
шапсуги пошли на территорию Турции
because  Turkey promised them something there,
потому что Турции там что-то им обещала
but as always, of their own free will, yes. As
но как всегда по доброй воле да В
a result, the defeat of the war with Russia. Yes,
результате поражение войны с Россией Да
and they left of their own free will. Well, yes, no, I  I
и по доброй воле ушли Ну да нет нет Я
mean Yes, defeat is a
имею в виду Да поражение - это
violent act, as it were, but to
насильственные как бы сказать акт А вот
stay or leave is the Adygs themselves, oh,
остаться или уйти это уже сами Адыги ой
these same Shapsugs chose them, no one
эти самые шапсуги выбирали их же никто
drove them out Yes And who are you
гнал Да А вы кто по национальности
by nationality? I am Russian by nationality, Russian, and that
Я русский по национальности русский а то
is, you are an occupier of our
есть вы оккупант получается наших
territories.  No, the occupier is you, you are
территорий Нет оккупант - это вы вы
the occupier, don’t wait, I’m a Circassian, I’ve lived on these
оккупант не подождите Я черкес Я на этих
lands for centuries, and you Russians
землях жил и покон веков А вы русские
came and conquered.
пришли завоевали
No, but the Circassians also came from and conquered
Нет так а черкесы тоже пришли завоевали
from where  the Circassians came the Circassians here are
откуда черкесы пришли черкесы тут
autochthonous and what have they always lived there
автохтонный а что они там всегда жили
or something? And where did they come from? Well, where did they
что ли А откуда они пришли Ну так откуда
come from where did the Circassians come from where did the
пришли откуда пришли черкесы откуда
Circassians roll out burnt
отку выкате подгорели черкес
autochthonous as long as the Russians where they were
автохтонные покуда че русские где были
that's where the Moscow principality is there
вот где там Московское княжество там вот
in Zalesye Yes from there they came like here
это в Залесье Да оттуда пришли типа сюда
conquered and the Shapsug ladies have been here since time
завоевали а шапсуги дамы тут из покон
immemorial, all the toponymy is here. Nani has
веков тут вся топонимика Нани покон
n’t been there for centuries. They haven’t lived there since time immemorial.
веков не было Не жили там из покон веков
the niche was originally the whole territory was
ниша изначально э вся территория была
Circassian, it’s like Russian, that’s when the century or
Черкесская это как рус вот когда век или
there the 10th century when the Russians conquered Taraka,
там X век когда завоевали тарака там
but what century did you come from and
русские жили А вот вы какой век пришли а
where are you from? This is what you came there in the 10th century
да какой откуда вы это самое вы в X веке
in which you came
туда пришли в каком в м Вы припёрлись
or in  look, we are one of the Kore We are
или в каком смотри мы один из коре Мы
one of the indigenous peoples of the Russian
один из коренных народов Российской
Federation Yes, in the century you called
Федерации Да себя называли в веке вы в X
yourself indigenous
веке себя коренными
now
назвали сейчас
Yes, we are the indigenous people of the Russian
Да нас коренной народ Российской
Federation who lived in our own and
Федерации который мы жили на своих и
quiet territories Yes we  We didn’t
спокойных территориях Да мы ниоткуда не
come from anywhere, we were formed here as an
приходили мы сформировались тут как
Ethnicity. Yes, in these territories we are Circassians.
Этнос Да на этих территориях мы черкесы
Yes, you committed the genocide of our ancestors. Yes,
Да вы устроили геноцид наших предков Да
your Yermolovskys, and now you’re still
ваши ермоловские и сейчас ещё вы
saying that we’ve come close to you, you’re so
говорите что мы припёрлись вы так
disrespectful to us. You
неуважительно к нам
say disrespectful, that’s because you’re
Говорите Не уважительно это же это же вы
disrespectful. You really speak to the Russians.  in
неуважительно Говорите к русским на
fact, well, because you are occupiers, you are
самом деле Ну потому что вы оккупанты вы
occupiers. Let me tell you once again that
оккупанты Давай я тебе ещё раз скажу
strong peoples conquered Shapsug  weak
шапсуг сильные народы покоряли слабые
peoples but no one Show well, show
народы но никто Покажи хорошо покажите
in these territories Yes, some of your
на этих территориях Да ваши какие-то
Russian religious buildings there are from the
российские там культовые сооружения там
15th century century
XV века века
Show So you yourself
Покажи Так ты сам
Show ho ska You said that you are
Покажи хо ска Ты же сказал что вы
autochthonous, well show that all
автохтоны ну покажи что тут все
the toponymy here is all Circassian
топонимика вся Черкесская
here, what is your Russian here?  what
тут что вашего тут русского есть что
does Sochi mean? What does
означает Сочи Что означает что означает
Sochi or Gelendzhik mean
Сочи или Геленджик
in Russian? Dear, what does Adler mean
по-русски Уважаемый что Адлер означает
in Russian? Now I’ll tell you, you can be
по-русски сейчас скажу ты ты можешь
silent for 2 minutes No  I can’t that Sugi
помолчать 2 минуты Нет не могу что суги
sa self-name
са самоназвание
Adyghe subos subethnos Adyghe in the past
адыге субос субэтнос адыга в прошлом
one of the largest Adyghe tribes
одно из крупнейших адыгских племён
lives in Adygea Adygea still
проживает в Адыгее Адыгея до сих пор
exists in the Krasnodar region and none
существует в Краснодарском крае и никто
of these Shapsugas who call themselves Adygs have
вот этих шапсуга которые себя адыгами
ever evicted them.
называют никто их не выселял Ещё раз
Look again at the map of Great Circassia See
посмотри карту Великой Черкесии Посмотри
how many  the entire Krasnodar region is the
сколько бы весь Краснодарский край - это
great Circassia, yes, when Russia took,
великая Черкесия да Когда Россия взяла
captured these lands, yes, drove them out  The
захватила эти земли Да выгнала Оставила
republic left us there Yes, there is a small
там нам республика Да вот там маленькая
Adygei, you will have a small Kabardian
адыгей у вас будет маленькая кабардина
Balkaria Yes, a small Karachay Cherkessia
Балкария Да маленькая карачаева Черкесия
Live there for yourself and Keep your head down
Живите там себе и Это не высовывайтесь
Sochi Tell me what Sochi means in Russian
Сочи Скажи что по-русски означает Сочи
Adler Gelendzhik Chemitokvadzhe
Адлер Геленджик чемитоквадже
Why do you have all the names Yes, they are not
Почему у вас все названия Да не
Russian I’m explaining to you because  The
русские Я тебе объясняю потому что
Russian Empire never engaged in
никогда Российская империя не занималась
genocide and did not have a name because
геноцидом и не имела название потому что
once it’s named, you get
то раз назва то получается у вас
a name, you came  here during the
название вы пришли сюда во время
Russian Empire you see
Российской империи видите вы
invaders Yes, during the Russian
захватчики Да во время Российской
Empire in the 10th century there were these names,
империи в X веке были эти названия
that’s why they left them all, that is,
поэтому их и оставили всё то есть пришли
you came here for literally 150 years Yes, somewhere
вы вы тут буквально 150 лет Да где-то
here in these territories you are occupiers
тут на этих территориях вы оккупанты
who came to the
которые пришли на всё
ready-made Circassians yes  And
готовеньком черкесов да Вот и сейчас
now you’re sitting here like this, crazy, without a
сейчас сидите вот такие тут без ума без
home, as they say, and you start
э дома Как говорится и начинаете что-то
broadcasting something that you have Russians, no literature,
вещать что у вас Русские ни литературы
no culture. You didn’t have Russians walking around in bast shoes.
ни культуры У вас что не было в лаптях
Yes, they even came  you
ходили русские Да даже пришли вы у нас
all took a checker from us - this is Circassian Yes,
все взяли шашка - это Черкесская Да
a hat is Circassian, everything you had
папаха это Черкесская всё что у вас было
walked around in bast shoes, ate turnips Yes, tell
ходили в лаптях репу ели Да вот назовите
me the Russian national
мне Русское национальное
dish What Russian national dish
блюдо Какое Русское национальное блюдо
Tell me Lomonosov Lomonosov
Расскажите ты Ломоносова Ломоносова
Tolstoy heard these there So you
Толстого слышал там эти Так ты мне вот
tell me without Lomonosov Tolstoy  What kind of
скажи без Ломоносова Толстого Какой у
Russians were you like before you came here
вас русских до того как вы пришли сюда
to our God-given Caucasus? What kind of food did you have,
на наш Богом данный Кавказ Да что у вас
spelt turnips?  Pushkin described this in the Tale of the
полба Пушкин так и описывал в Сказке о
Priest, his workers Balda Yes, spelt
попе его работники Балде Да полбу жрали
ate turnips, it’s clear, do you
репу понятно понятно А ты греческого
know the Greek of this Mithridates or
греческого этого митридата знаешь или
not And don’t tell me about
нет И ещё ты мне не рассказывай про
Greek Come on, I’m a native Yes I am, you
греческий Давай я коренной Да я ты
live on my land, you’re
живёшь на моей земле ты временный тут
not even a temporary guest here  guest guest - this is the one
гость даже не гость гость - это тот
who was asked Yes, you are a temporary
которого попросили Да ты временный как
tenant, are
бы квартирант не
you not coming to my land? Yes, you are humiliating my
ты прил на мою землю Да ты унижаешь мою
land, here now you are exploiting it. Yes,
землю тут сейчас ты эксплуатирует её Да
you are
ты
inhabited by all these strange people we are here Great Circassia must be restored Sochi Adler Gelendzhik everything must return to the Great Cherka Yes VN This is your prince and so far away your invaders must be back Here in your Zalesye here in the times of Rus' Kyiv allocated you behind the forests to Moscow, where I ran away for Les, that’s where and in short, get out of here, it’s so cool, I played the Circassian man all the way
населяет этих всяких непонятных людей мы
blown up look how They hate
подорвался смотрите как Они ненавидят
Russians very important now it will be yes uh
русские очень важный сейчас будет да ээ
summary How Russians hate
резюме Как русские ненавидят
everyone All the peoples of the Russian Federation yes
всех Все народы Российской Федерации да
when they need They say we are a
когда им нужно Говорят мы
multinational country we have 10,000
многонациональная страна у нас там 10000
people there and so on And when so you are
народов и так дальше А когда так вы это
something we are here you are the Circassian came And  We are
чтото мы тут это вы черкес пришла А мы
here from time immemorial, Russian, yes, the Russians
тут из спокон веков русский да у русских
had them everywhere And everyone else
они всюду были А все остальные по
came Yes, the Ukrainians came to Ukraine from somewhere, the
приходили Да украинцы откуда-то пришли в
Circassians Yes, they came to their lands
Украину черкесы Да на свои земли пришли
Yes, the Buryats came, the Tatars And so on That's how
да буряты пришли татары И так дальше Вот
cool it is, its collapse like sand comment
так классно его развал лайк песка комент
Glory to
Слава
Ukraine write to th Telegram right now
Украине пись на й Telegram прямо зараз
axis VN
ось ВН
apok tse even more and more politely YouTube taking
апок це дуже и дуже важливо YouTube заня
us through the skarg ODS in your ban and even
нас через скарг ОРВ в твый бан и дуже
more videos I don’t show people at all times I don’t
багато вдео не показую людям вчасно не
show them  information about streaming Tom for this
показуе информация про стрими Тому для
purpose, you need to write an operational link in Mali
того щоб ми Мали оперативный звязок
directly at the same time and Popik there in
пишиться прямо зараз а Попик там в
Telegra okrim video is also the same Tsikava and
телегра окрим видео ще теж е цикава и
Korisna information and we are responsible for you
корисна информация и мы повинни з вами
trimati postiyny operational link
тримати постийний оперативный звязок
nezalezhno in that chi show you about it
незалежно в того чи покаже вам про це
YouTube Slava Ukraine
YouTube Слава украини
write N
пиши N